Guide to the Records of the Washington Square Counselor to Women Students (Berger) RG.19.4
New York University Archives
Records of the Washington Square Counselor to Women Students (Berger)
1952-1966
New York University Archives
RG.19.4
1.5 Linear Feet in 3 boxes
Dorothea Berger was born in 1907 and educated in Germany. She came to Washington Square College in 1949 as an instructor in the German Language Department. By 1962, she had become Assistant to the Dean of Students as well as Counselor for Women Students. She was made a full professor in 1966 and became emeritus in 1973. These papers are collection of administrative correspondence collected while in the Dean's administration and reveal various aspects of women student activities and life in the 1950's and 1960's.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading.
The files are grouped into one series.
Scope and Content Note
The collection reveals a much less powerful role for the administrator for women's interests. Berger, a counselor rather than a dean, usually reported through an associate dean, the Dean of Students to the Dean of Washington Square College. Her main duties were counseling in strictly non?academic areas, advising the Association of Women Students (formerly League of Women), the Committee of Junior Advisors and chairing the senior and junior tutors committee. She also advised the Student Council.
The most valuable student activities files are files on the organization of the University Christian Foundation, the activities of Gamma Gamma Sigma, Association of Women Students and Pan?Hellenic. Berger's files, especially the Day Organization, indicate that she was not as exclusively concerned with women students as her predecessor. While she held this position, the emphasis seemed to shift away from women students towards all student affairs.
Berger seems to have inherited and continued the use of some of Dorothy Arnold's files. For ongoing organizations such as the Association of Women Students, the Junior Advisors, Eclectic and Gamma Gamma Sigma this was a logical action for a successor. However some files from Dorothy Arnold's era has had little or nothing added to them by Dorothea Berger.
This is the case for the following folders: Judson Residence, Faculty Women's Lounges, Bucker, Mildred Parker and four Arnold annual reports to the Dean. This material should probably be included in the Arnold collection. One file, Administrative Management Council, begins in 1971,after the date of Berger's return to teaching. It belongs more properly in either her personal papers or in her successors' files.
The files end with the letter "R" indicating that more material may be in the Dean of Washington Square and University College offices. The files are arranged alphabetically bra subject or correspondent. Each folder is arranged chronologically with the earliest dates in the front of each folder. The Berger papers are not as substantial as the Arnold Berger Papers and should be used as supplementary materials.
Biographical/Historical note
Dorothea Berger received her M.A. from the University of Berlin and Ph.D.from the University of Bonn am Rheim. She came to Washington Square College in 1949 as an instructor in the German Language Department. In 1954 she became an Assistant Professor. She became a student counselor in 1959 and received a promotion to Associate Professor. In 1960 she became Acting Chairman of the German Language Department and remained a part of the teaching faculty until September 1961 when she became the successor to Dean Dorothy Arnold. Rather than Dean of Women, she received the title Counselor for Women Students. She did not report directly to the Dean of the College but to the Dean of Students. Her administrative powers and responsibilities were smaller than Dean Arnold's. In 1962 she became Assistant to the Dean of Students as well as Counselor for Women Students. In this capacity, she worked more closely with another office, Counseling and Advisory Services, than had her predecessor.
In 1965 another woman, Elsa Robinson, joined the Dean of Students' office as an Assistant to the Dean for Advisement and as a Counselor. In the Spring of 1966 Berger was one of seven assistants to the Dean for Advisement. The Fall of 1966 found Berger teaching again, as a full professor. Elsa Robinson was her apparent successor as counselor for women students.
Dorothea Berger became emeritus in 1973.
Sources:
Arts & Sciences, Faculty of WSC: Reminiscences, Berger, Dorothea July 8, 1963.
Access Restrictions
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
Provenance
The Records of the Washington Square Counselor to Women Students (Berger) are the administrative files of the successor to the Dean of Women's office and were accessioned from the Dean of Washington Square and University College.
Related Materials
Records of the Dean of Women, Washington Square College, Dorothy McSparran Arnold
Clippings (information artifacts); New York (N.Y.); Memorandums.; Washington Square College of Arts and Science |x Faculty.; Photographs.; Correspondence.; Washington Square College |x Administration.; New York University |x Societies.; New York University -- History.; Washington Square College of Arts and Science |x Students.; Women's rights.; Washington Square College of Arts and Science |x History.; New York University; Parker, Mildred; Washington Square College of Arts and Science. University Christian Foundation; Washington Square College. Women's Office; Arnold, Dorothea; Berger, Dorothea; Gamma Gamma Sigma (Association of Women Students)
- Series I
  - Administration Appointments and Assignments; Correspondence, memos, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Group, 1958-1959, 1961, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, minutes, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Administrative Management Council; Correspondence, minutes, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alumni Achievement Award - Selection; Correspondence, minutes, 1954-1957, 1960, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Association of Women Students (formerly League of Women, change October 1961);Constitution, correspondence, 1956-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Association of Women Students Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Buckler, William E. Dean; Scholarship Award Lists and Correspondence, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - University Christian Foundation; Correspondence, minutes, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - University Christian Foundation; Constitution, History, Membership lists, Report on the Student Christian Movement, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Office of Counselling Services; Forms, reports, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Crosman, Arthur "Report of High School Averages; and Test Scores - to College Performance", 1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Day Organization, Washington Square College; Correspondence, minutes, lists of officers; Correspondence, minutes, lists of officers, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Reports to the Dean (WSC); Correspondence; Correspondence, 1945-1954 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Reports to the Dean (WSC); Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Dean's List (WSC), 1961-1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dean of Students Office; Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Eclectic Society Membership & Selection; Lists, correspondence, 1949-1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Eclectic Society Membership & Selection; Lists, correspondence, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Eclectic Society Membership & Selection; Lists, correspondence, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Eclectic Society Membership & Selection; Lists, correspondence, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Eclectic Society Membership & Selection; Lists, correspondence, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Eclectic Society Forms, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Faculty Advisement System; Minutes, memos, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Faculty Women's Lounge; Correspondence, 1941-1958 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Faculty Women's Lounge Maintenance; Correspondence, requisitions, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Judson Residence, policy, complaints, residents, 1952-1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Gamma Gamma Sigma (Sorority, service); Constitution, correspondence, 1952-1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Judson Residence, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bradley, Lyman R. (prof.) clippings, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, communism, 1947-1949, 1951-1952, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Committee of Junior Advisers, 1956, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Committee of Junior Advisers, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Committee of Junior Advisers, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Loeb Student Center, 1955-1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Loeb Student Center, 1958-1963 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Pan-Hellenic, 1959-1960, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - NYU, General (clippings), 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - NYU Students and Alumni(ae), 1936 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Parents Reception, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Parents Reception, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Mrs. Parker's Correspondence, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Residences for Women, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Women's Athletics, 1935, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Women's Service Organization, circa 1940s (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Sororities (clippings), 1952-1955 (Box 3, Folder 18)